Guide to the James H. Pou, Sr. correspondence, 1865-1944 RL.11840
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Hinton Pou, Sr. correspondence
1865-1944
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pou, James H. (James Hinton), 1861-1935
RL.11840
6.5 Linear Feet 9 boxes; 1 oversize folder Approx. 4065 items
Collection consists of the personal and professional correspondence of James Hinton Pou, Sr., lawyer, politician, and land developer of Raleigh, North Carolina. Topics cover late 19th and early 20th century North Carolina politics and legal system, business and land development in North Carolina, the history of Raleigh, N.C. and Wake County, and the Pou-Bailey families.
Arrangement
The correspondence is arranged in chronological order.
Biographical / Historical
James Hinton Pou, Sr. (1861-1935), a lawyer, politician, and land developer based in Raleigh, North Carolina, was born in Tuskegee, Alabama, to Edward William and Anna Maria Smith Pou of Johnston County, N.C. The family moved to Johnston County after the Civil War. Pou began practicing the legal profession in Raleigh, and soon joined the practice of his relative by marriage Josiah Bailey, and later with his son, James H. Pou, Jr.
In the period of Reconstruction politics Pou emerged as an active, articulate Democrat and served three terms in the General Assembly: in 1885 as a representative and in 1888 and 1892 as a senator. Although he was urged to pursue a career in politics, he chose to devote his time to his law practice.
In 1889, Pou was married to Annie Walker. They had two children, James H. Pou, Jr., and Edith Walker Pou, who married Josiah Bailey, whose papers are also available in the Rubenstein Library.
James H. Pou died in Raleigh, N.C. in 1935 and is buried in Oakwood Cemetery.
[From DICTIONARY OF NORTH CAROLINA BIOGRAPHY: VOLUME 5, P-S edited by William S. Powell. Copyright © 1994 by the University of North Carolina Press. Used by permission of the publisher. www.uncpress.org]
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The James Hinton Pou, Sr. correspondence was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1970.
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of the personal and professional correspondence of James Hinton Pou, Sr., a lawyer, businessman, and land developer of Raleigh, North Carolina. Topics cover late 19th and early 20th century North Carolina politics and legal system, business and land development in North Carolina, the history of Raleigh, N.C. and Wake County, and the Pou-Bailey families of central North Carolina. Other items mixed in with the correspondence may include memorabilia, bills, and receipts.
Related Materials
Related collection: James Pou Bailey papers, 1901-1970, Rubenstein Library, Duke University.
Related collection: Josiah William Bailey papers, 1833-1967, Rubenstein Library, Duke University.
Lawyers -- Correspondence; Lawyers -- North Carolina -- Raleigh; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Raleigh (N.C.) -- History; Raleigh (N.C.) -- Politics and government; Wake County (N.C.) -- History
- Correspondence, 1865-1913 May (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1913 June-1916 Feb. (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1916 March-Dec. (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1917 Jan.-Sept. (Box 4)
- Correspondence, 1917 Oct.-1918 Sept. (Box 5)
- Correspondence, 1919 March-1920 March (Box 6)
- Correspondence, 1920 April-1921 Jan. (Box 7)
- Correspondence, 1921 Feb.-1944 (Box 8)
- Additional papers (Box 1 (addition))
- Oversize papers (Oversize-folder 1)